Okay today's דף daf is יב, yud bet, בבא קמא Bava Kamma
12, and we pick up at the very top line of יב
עמוד א. yud bet amud aleph. Our learning should be in the
זכות zechus of the protection of our חיילים chayalim and חיילות chayalot
and all the innocent people whose lives are at risk right now
and we and the protection of עם ישראל Am Yisrael מדינת ישראל.
Medinat Yisrael. Okay, so we are now in the midst of a
list of statements from Ulla in the name of Rabbi Elazar and
the most recent one was that גובין מן העבדים, govin min ha-avadim,
that debts can be collected from slaves meaning that the same way
there is a lien on real estate, on land, there's a lien
on slaves which means that if the debtor sold it to a
third party or died and his heirs inherited the creditors could collect
from the slaves the same way they could collect from real estate,
something they could not do by chattel. Now that was challenged by
Rav Nachman and Rav Nachman seemed to say wait that doesn't make
any sense he seemed to reject the idea that there would be
a lien on a slave which caused Ulla to double back and
Ulla said no no no I'm only talking about when there's actually
an אפותיקי, apotiki, an explicit lien that was placed on the slave
that would work, it would not work if it was a normal
chattel like on cattle but if it was an explicit document that
placed a lien on a slave that would work but I don't
mean that just as a general rule there are liens on slaves
as a general rule liens only take place on land on real
estate. Okay that was at least how Ulla responded when he was
challenged by Rav Nachman. But now we pick up at the top
of יב עמוד א yud bet amud aleph and we're going to
see that that was not really his position. So לבתר דנפק, le-basar
de-nafak, after Rav Nachman left אמר להו amleu Ulla, Ulla said to
the people that were there הכי אמר hachi amar Rabbi Elazar, you
should know that here is really what Rabbi Elazar said not like
we're talking only when an explicit אפותיקי apotiki was placed but אפילו
מיתמי afilu mi-yasmei that the it genuinely is a lien on slaves
that you can collect even from the heirs if the person dies
or from the third parties who purchase it that there is a
lien on slaves the same way there is a lien on real
estate. Okay. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, so apparently Rav Nachman
heard about this and he said אשתמיטיתן ishtamititen Ulla, Ulla is sort
of getting out of his position he's avoiding stating you know what
he really holds from I mean he's holding back from me his
real position because clearly Rav Nachman as we as we just heard
very strongly rejected the idea that there could be a lien on
slave without an official אפותיקי. apotiki. So Ulla rather than directly confronting
Rav Nachman and saying yes my tradition is that there can sort
of avoided the conversation. But Ulla's actual position from Rabbi Elazar is
yes there is a lien on slaves. So now we're going to
continue and see that you know the weight seems to be following
Ulla's practice. So let's take a look. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav
Nachman, so
apparently הוה עובדא בנהרדעא, hava uvda be-Neharde'a, there was a case in
Neharde'a which is where Shmuel was the authority
and also you know Rav Nachman Shmuel's student was the authority in
Neharde'a. הוה עובדא בנהרדעא ואגבו דייני דנהרדעא, Hava uvda be-Neharde'a ve-agvu dayyane
d'Neharde'a, and the judges of Neharde'a actually were prepared to collect a
lien from slaves, assume that if somebody lent money that gave them
a lien not only on land but also on slaves. They followed
the teaching of Ulla in the name of Rabbi
Elazar. הוה עובדא בפומבדיתא, Hava uvda be-Pumbedita, there was also a case
in Pumbedita ואגבי ve-agbe Rav Chana bar Bizna and Rav Chana bar
Bizna allowed the creditor to collect from slaves that were either passed
on to the heirs or were sold to a third party. So
you see everybody is ruling that slaves are fully like property and
there's a lien on slaves the same way there's a lien on
property and this was the teaching of Ulla in the name of
Rabbi Elazar. So but Rav Nachman continues to disagree. אמר להו Amar
lehu Rav Nachman, so Rav Nachman said to the judges
זילו אהדורי, zilu ahadureh, go reverse the judgment or he said to
you know Rav Chana bar Bizna go reverse the judgment give these
slaves back to the debtor or back to the third party I
should say the purchasers there is no lien on slaves. זילו אהדורי
ואי לא, Zilu ahaduru ve-ilo, and if you don't מגבינן לכו אפדנייכו,
magbinan lechu apandaichu, I will he was saying to the judges I
will take your castles from you meaning I will seize your houses
in payment that you have actually judged incorrectly and this was a
complete error. Alright so Rav Nachman strongly feels that there are no
liens on slaves and the creditor does not have a right to
collect slaves that were sold to third parties. אמר ליה רבא לרב
נחמן, Amar leh Rava le-Rav Nachman, so finally somebody's going to push
back against Rav Nachman's objection. Said Rava to Rav Nachman הא עולא.
ha Ulla. One minute. עולא Ula clearly holds there are liens on
slaves. הא רבי אליעזר, Ha Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds
it. רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, עולא Ula was teaching in the name
of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. הא דיינא דנהרדעא, Ha Dayana DiNehardea, and
we have the case of that happened in נהרדעא, Nehardea, the judges
of נהרדעא Nehardea clearly feel that. והא רב חנה בר ביזנא, Ve-ha
Rav Chana bar Bizna, and there's also רב חנה בר ביזנא Rav
Chana bar Bizna in פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. You have all of these people
that hold, all of these positions that there are liens on slaves,
and slaves are considered like, like land. מר כמאן סבירא ליה? Mar
keman svara lei? Who do you hold like that you think that
there are not liens on slaves? So אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said, אנא מתניתא ידענא. Ana matnita yedana. Look, it's very nice to
quote me all those authorities. I don't know about those authorities. All
I know, I'm a simple ייד. Yid. All I know is the
ברייתא. Braita. What ברייתא Braita is it that I know of? אנא
מתניתא ידענא. Ana matnita yedana. I'm
sorry, what line? דתני אבימי, De-tani Avimi, אבימי Avimi taught a ברייתא,
Braita, פרוזבול חל על הקרקע ואינו חל על העבדים. Pruzbol chal al
ha-karka ve-eino chal al ha-avadim. If you write a פרוזבול, Pruzbol, the
thing that allows somebody to collect the debt after שמיטה, Shmita, so
the הלכה Halacha was that it could only be written if the
debtor has at least some piece of land. So he says that
that will work if the debtor has a piece of land, but
not if the debtor has a slave. Now what's the logic? So
the way to understand this is that if I have a lien,
if I'm the creditor, let's say, and I have a lien on
land against the debtor, the reason that the, you know, the שמיטה
Shmita annuls it because it is because I can't sort of demand
collectment of the debt. But if there's land and the land is
available and I have a lien on it for me to seize
it at any time, it's as if, you know, I already have
that debt under my control because I can take that land and
it's there at any time. Okay, and that is true if there's
land to the debtor but not if there is a slave. So
that seems to show that there are no liens on slaves. Okay,
could maybe be based on other things, but at least on the
face of it, it seems to be that it works for land
because there are liens, and if it's not working for slaves, it's
because there are no liens on slaves.
That's number one.
Number two, so that's a principle of liens. Now, and we're going
to, and now let's look at another area in which this question
of are slaves treated like land or not like land? So,
so continuing this ברייתא, Braita, מטלטלין נקנין עם הקרקע ואינם נקנין עם
העבדים. Metaltelin niknim im ha-karka ve-einam niknim im ha-avadim. You can take
possession of chattel together with, together with land, but
not together with slaves. So what does this mean? There's a principle
we learn in קידושין Kiddushin called קנין אגב, Kinyan Agav, that when
you take possession of land, if the person is trying to sell
you or transfer ownership of chattel as well, even if the chattel
isn't on the land, I want to go ahead and I want
to sell you my car, my watch, or whatever, and you're taking
possession of land, I say, by your taking possession of this land,
you will also take possession of my watch wherever it is, you
know, and then that works. That's considered a קנין אגב. Kinyan Agav.
So that works when you take possession of קרקע, Karka, if the
seller or the gift-giver wants to give you chattel, that will go
together with the קנין Kinyan of the קרקע Karka wherever that chattel
is. So that works with מטלטלין, Metaltelin, but it does not work
with slaves. So you see by both of these that slaves are
considered to be, I'm sorry, מטלטלין נקנין עם הקרקע ואינם נקנין עם
העבדים, Metaltelin niknim im ha-karka ve-einam niknim im ha-avadim, excuse me, right.
If you take possession of slaves, you do not take possession of
chattel. Okay, so in both of these, slaves do not work like
land. They are not liens, there's liens on land and you can
write a פרוזבול, Pruzbol, but there's not a lien on slave, that's
implicit and therefore you can't write a פרוזבול. Pruzbol. So a slave
is not like
land, עבדא לאו כקרקעי דמי, Avda lav kemarkei damei, it's not like
קרקע. Karka. And number two, when you take possession of land you
can be קונה Koneh with אגב Agav מטלטלין, Metaltelin, chattel, but when
you take possession of slaves you cannot be קונה Koneh מטלטלין Metaltelin
through אגב, Agav, so you see that slaves are like chattel, are
like מטלטלין, Metaltelin, they are not like land. Now, we'll just pause
here because, you know, תוספות Tosfos notes that in all other places
in ש"ס, Shas, the assumption is that עבד Eved is כקרקעי, Kemarkei,
a slave is like land. That when you're exempt, for example, from
taking an oath, or overcharging, or all of these categories of exemptions
that the things don't apply to land, they
also, you know, גניבה וגזילה בקרקע ובעבדים, Gneiva ve-gezeila bi-karka u-be-avadim, that
if they don't apply to land, they don't apply to slaves. So
what is the whole issue here about whether slaves are like land
or not? We know that slaves and lands are usually in the
same category. So תוספות Tosfos says that the question is by things
that are rabbinic. Do we treat slaves like land even for rabbinic
הלכות? Halachot? And the two הלכות Halachot we're looking here about
liens on land and on slaves, or פרוזבול, Pruzbol, which is a
rabbinic הלכה, Halacha, or אגב, Agav, this way that when you're קונה,
Koneh, when you take possession of land you take possession of chattel,
תוספות Tosfos says those are all rabbinic, and that's the question: should
we extend the category slaves equals land? even to rabbinic areas. It's
not so clear why we should change the category. Once slaves are
like lands for
תורה Torah דאורייתא d'oraissa laws, why should they not be it for
rabbinic laws? The other way to think about it is things that
are like more formal exemptions or things that are more like real,
where how things are actually the role they play in society really
matters. Slaves maybe are seen like land to some degree
because they are property that lasts for a long time, they work
the land, they are maybe things that are inherited and passed down,
והתנחלתם
אתם לבניכם אחריכם, vehisnachaltem osam livneichem achareichem, the תורה Torah actually speaks
about slaves in that way that it's a type of an inheritance
that's passed down. So as a technical formal category, if you're exempt
in some הלכות halachot from land, you could be exempt from slaves.
But that doesn't explain how they function in society.
And the question about liens, well the reason there's liens on land
and not on chattel is because land doesn't move around and you
know exactly what the land is and you can have very clear
records about who owns which piece of property and that makes it
fair for purchasers who can have access to that information. That doesn't
play out exactly the same way with slaves.
So that's in terms of like the liens issue and פרוזבול pruzbul
maybe goes with it. And this idea of taking possession of land
and taking possession of chattel, all of those are areas in which
have to do with more of how they function in society and
that maybe is a different category. But for one reason or another
within these areas of liens and קניינים, kinyanim, the גמרא Gemara wants
to know are slaves like land or not. So we have עולא
Ulla in the name of רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar and a whole
list of דיינים dayanim that said that there were sort of liens
on slaves, slaves are like land. And רב נחמן Rav Nachman is
resisting it and he's quoting this ברייתא braisa and saying no, no
פרוזבול pruzbul on slaves, אגב agav doesn't work when you're take possession
of a slave, you don't get אגב agav with מטלטלין, metaltelin, slaves
are like chattel, they are not like land. So that is the
debate at least in these two areas. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says לימא כתנאי, leima k'tana'ei, let's say
this debate of רב נחמן Rav Nachman who says slaves are not
like land and עולא Ulla and רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar who says
they are, let's say this is a debate of תנאים. tanna'im. לימא
כתנאי: leima k'tana'ei: מכר לו עבדים וקרקעות, machar lo avadim vekarka'os, if
somebody sold, ראובן Reuven sold to שמעון Shimon slaves and land, והחזיק
בעבדים, vehechezik ba'avadim, took possession of the slave, לא קנה קרקע, lo
kanah karka, you don't take possession of the land. ובקרקע לא קנה
עבדים, ubekarka lo kanah avadim, if you take possession of land you
don't take possession of the slave. So slaves seem to be, you
know the simple sense here is that they're not functioning like chattel,
because if they were functioning like chattel, if you took possession of
קרקע karka you would take possession of the slave. So it seems
here that slaves are considered to be like land or they're in
a third category, but when you take possession of slaves you don't
take possession of land and vice versa. לא קנה קרקע. lo kanah
karka.
Let's do the...
okay.
Now however קרקעות ומטלטלין, karka'os umetaltelin, if you had slaves and chattel,
החזיק בקרקע קנה מטלטלין, hechezik bekarka kanah metaltelin, במטלטלין לא קנה קרקע.
bimetaltelin lo kanah karka. If you take possession of the land you
take possession of the chattel, but not vice versa. That's the principle
of the קניין אגב. kinyan agav. עבדים ומטלטלין, avadim umetaltelin, now if
you had slaves and chattel, החזיק בעבדים לא קנה מטלטלין, hechezik ba'avadim
lo kanah metaltelin, if you take possession of the slave you don't
take possession of the chattel. במטלטלין לא קנה עבדים, bimetaltelin lo kanah
avadim, if you take possession of the chattel you don't take possession
of the slaves.
So all of this works,
it's basically slaves don't work together with anything. They don't work together
with קרקע karka and they don't work together with מטלטלין metaltelin and
to some degree they may be even seen like a third category
by themselves. Okay, so taking possession of מטלטלין metaltelin or קרקע karka
or slaves, you don't get sort of the other one with it.
Now that's one ברייתא. braisa.
We'll see the גמרא Gemara is going to sort of work through
the details of this. ותניא vetanya but we have a different ברייתא
braisa that teaches החזיק בעבדים קנה מטלטלין hechezik ba'avadim kanah metaltelin that
if you take possession of slaves you do take possession of chattel.
So without sort of working through all the permutations, let's focus on
the one that's been our focus, which is does קניין אגב kinyan
agav work? If you take possession of a slave, you take possession
of מטלטלין. metaltelin. Does it work like קרקע karka when you take
possession of קרקע karka you take possession of מטלטלין? metaltelin? So the
first ברייתא braisa said no, it does not work with אגב, agav,
and the second ברייתא braisa here said yes, it does work with
אגב. agav. So we're going to have to figure out all the
permutations but at least zooming in on this particular issue, when you
take the slaves do you get the מטלטלין, metaltelin, if that's debated,
that seems to be our issue. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, mai lav
beha kamiflegi, isn't that that this is the debate? דמר סבר עבדים
כמקרקעי דמי, demar savar avadim kemikarkei dami, that this second ברייתא braisa
holds that slaves are like land and therefore if you take possession
of slaves you can do אגב agav and get מטלטלין metaltelin with
it.
ומר סבר עבדים כמטלטלי דמי, umar savar avadim kemetalteli dami, no they're
like chattel and if you take possession of one you do not
take possession if you take possession of one piece of chattel
Okay, so again without getting into the permutations just yet, these ברייתות
braitot disagree whether being קנה koneh a slave allows you to do
אגב agav for מטלטלין. metaltelin. That seems to be exactly our debate.
אמר רב איקא בריה דרב אמי, Amar Rav Ika b'rei d'Rav Ami,
so said רב איקא Rav Ika son of רב אמי: Rav Ami:
No, דכולי עלמא עבדים כמקרקעי דמי. de-chulei alma avadim ke-mika-rke-dami. I can
explain these ברייתות braitot that everybody holds slaves are like קרקע, karka,
so you should be able to do אגב. agav. והדתניא קנה, Ve-ha-d'tanya
kana, so the one that says you can use a slave and
do אגב agav with מטלטלין, metaltelin, שפיר, shapir, that works with the
idea that it's like קרקע. karka. והדתניא לא קנה, Ve-ha-d'tanya lo kana,
the idea that says that if you get the slave you don't
get the chattel, בעינן קרקע דומיא דערי מצורות ביהודה. be-inan karka dumya
de-arei mitzurot bi-Yehuda. Okay, so you do not, you know, it's—yes, it's
like קרקע, karka, but it's not like standard קרקע. karka. It's not
like the verse, we're going to see a verse that's the basis
of אגב, agav, that speaks about like the walled cities, you know,
in יהודה. Yehuda. So therefore,
it has to be real קרקע karka in order to work for
אגב. agav. It's a special הלכה halacha of אגב agav דלא ניידי,
de-lo naydi, that they don't move, that something's stable, it's not a
human being that moves around, it's real land. דתנן, Detnan, why should
I say that? That you need a special requirement for אגב? agav?
Because let's see what the basis of this קנין kinyan of אגב
agav is. נכסים שאין להם אחריות נקנים עם נכסים שיש להם אחריות
בכסף
ובשטר ובחזקה. Nechasim she-ein lahem achrayut niknim im nechasim she-yesh lahem achrayut
be-kesef u-vi-shtar u-ve-chazaka. Here's the principle, the משנה mishna in קידושין, Kiddushin,
things that do not have liens on them, meaning chattel, is that
you can take possession of them when you're taking possession of things
that do have liens, meaning when you're taking possession of קרקע, karka,
and how do you take possession of קרקע? karka? בכסף בשטר ובחזקה.
be-kesef u-vi-shtar u-ve-chazaka. Okay, classic ways in which you take possession of
land. That's the principle of אגב. agav. When you take possession of
land, if the owner wants to sell you chattel, the chattel can
also transfer. מנא הני מילי? Mena hani mili? And we teach on
that, where does this—what is this based on? אמר חזקיה דאמר קרא,
Amar Hizkiyah d'amar kra, the verse says: ויתן להם אביהם מתנות רבות
לכסף ולזהב ולמגדנות עם ערי מצורות ביהודה. Va-yiten lahem avihem matnot rabot
le-kesef u-le-zahav u-le-migdanot im arei mitzurot bi-Yehuda. Their father gave them many
gifts, silver and gold and
delicacies together with the walled cities of יהודה. Yehuda. So and from
there we learn that when they took possession of the walled cities
of יהודה, Yehuda, they took all of this other chattel together with
it. Okay, so what we're basically saying is: everybody could hold that
it functions like—that it's like קרקע karka for standard הלכות halachot and
maybe everybody would agree that there are liens on slaves, that's where
the debate started, but these ברייתות braitot would disagree whether a קנין
אגב kinyan agav works because even though technically they're like קרקע, karka,
again, they're like קרקע karka but they're not actual קרקע, karka, they're
human beings and they're moving around and for the קנין אגב kinyan
agav you might need real קרקע karka based on the פסוק. pasuk.
Especially if you want to conceptualize it, that it's like since you
could sort of put the chattel on the land, land is a
place, a repository for chattel, that works for real land, it doesn't
work for, you know, slaves. Okay, so that's the debate, but in
all other areas it would be like land. That would be how
you would defend
an עולא Ulla position and you know that it is like land.
That's one explanation. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say, אמר רב איקא
בריה דרב אידי, Amar Rav Ika b'rei d'Rav Idi, דכולי עלמא עבדי
כמטלטלין דמי. de-chulei alma avdi ke-metaltelin dami.
Let's go the opposite way. We'll defend a רב נחמן Rav Nachman
position. Slaves will be like chattel, there won't be any liens on
them. Okay, no liens. So then what's the ברייתא braita that says
you can use them for
אגב? agav? והדתניא לא קנה Ve-ha-d'tanya lo kana according to the ברייתא
braita that you did not take possession, you can't use them for
אגב, agav, שפיר, shapir, that works well. הדתניא קנה, Ha-d'tanya kana, the
ברייתא braita that says that you can use
them, בעודן עליו. be-oden alav. No, you misunderstood it. It's not referring
to the fact that you take possession of the slave and you
can take possession of my watch that's in a different state. That's
קנין אגב. kinyan agav. That's not true. Slaves are like מטלטלין. metaltelin.
So what does it mean that it can work? If the other
object is on the slave. The slave is wearing my watch. So
you take possession of my slave and you also take possession of
my watch because then when you take possession of my slave that
becomes like your property, it is your property, and then you take
possession of the watch that's on my slave because that's a קנין
חצר. kinyan chatzer. Alright, so it says that when you take possession
of slaves you take possession of chattel, and it sounds like it's
אגב, agav, but it's really not אגב, agav, it's a special case
of קנין חצר kinyan chatzer when the slave—when the property is on
the slave. וכי עודן עליו, Ve-chi oden alav, says the גמרא, Gemara,
if the property is on the slave, מאי הוי, mai hava, who
cares? חצר מהלכת היא, Chatzer mehalechet hi, the slave is still a
moving yard, a moving field, piece of property. קנין חצר Kinyan chatzer
presumably does not work if the property is
moving. וכי תימא בעומד, Ve-chi tema b'omed, that the slave is standing?
ואמר רבא כל שאילו מהלך לא קנה עומד ויושב לא קנה. Ve-amar
Rava kol she-illu mehalekh lo kana omed ve-yoshev lo kana. Rava says
that it doesn't matter that if somebody when they were walking would
not serve as a חצר chatzer because they have the ability to
walk and therefore they're not like a normal חצר chatzer and it's
not like it's normally under my control and
possession. So the way it will take, it will work that something
I can take possession of something on my slave is if my
slave is bound and therefore he doesn't have the ability to walk
and then he works like a piece of land. תוספות Tosafot discusses
that he also might have to be asleep so that the thing
is only being protected because I'm protecting it and not because my
slave is keeping an eye on it. So this is a very,
very דחוק dachuk explanation that basically it's not working by אגב, agav,
it's working by חצר chatzer in a very special case. So what
do we have? So we have this ברייתא braita that is very
complicated about
slaves and מטלטלין, metaltelin, slaves and קרקע karka and the whole thing,
but focusing in on the issue about does it work for אגב,
agav, one ברייתא braita says it does and one says it doesn't.
This would seem to be the debate about whether slaves are like
קרקע karka or not. And the גמרא Gemara has two explanations. One
is everybody could agree like עולא Ula that it's like קרקע karka
and there are liens, but it might not work for אגב agav
because it's not like the פסוק pasuk and it's not real property.
And the other is everybody could agree like רב נחמן Rav Nachman
there are no liens and maybe the way that it works is
not אגב agav but through a special circumstance and a קנין חצר.
kinyan chatzer. Fine. So now let's see ותניא va-tanya says the גמרא,
Gemara, okay, let's look at a different part of the ברייתא. braita.
Our ברייתא braita said that if you take possession of land you
don't take possession of slaves, the ברייתא braita we quoted before. We
have yet another ברייתא braita that says החזיק בקרקע קנה עבדים. hechzik
be-karka kanah avadim. If you take possession of land you do take
possession of slaves. Okay, so now we have to figure out what
these two ברייתות braitot are arguing about.
So let's understand what that's idea. Let's start with the ברייתא braita
that if you take possession of land you take possession of slaves.
How does that work?
התם Hatam says the גמרא Gemara בעומדים בתוכה be-omdim be-tokhah that the
slaves are standing in the property. So if, again, this would work
as we'll see in a minute, the גמרא Gemara will spell this
out, but if you say that slaves are like מטלטלין, metaltelin, then
when you take possession of land you take possession of slaves because
that could be like אגב. agav. Okay, but if slaves are like
קרקע, karka, then why when you take possession of land should it
work for the slaves? All right, does it work if you take
possession of one piece of land you take possession of another? That's
not so clear. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay,
we're going to figure this out as we go along. החזיק בקרקע
קנה עבדים. hechzik be-karka kanah avadim.
When you take possession of land, you take possession of slaves. התם
בעומדים בתוכה. Hatam be-omdim be-tokhah. The slaves are standing in the land.
מכלל דהאי לא קנה כשאינן עומדים בתוכה. Mikhlal de-hai lo kanah keshe-einan
omdim be-tokhah. So when it says you don't take possession, they're not
standing in the land, the first ברייתא. braita. הניחא ללישנא דאמר רב
איקא בריה דרב אידי עבדי כמטלטלי דמי. Ha nicha le-lishna de-amar Rav
Ika bereih de-Rav Idi avdi ke-metalteli dami.
So if you say slaves are like, now we're going to see
how to play out these ברייתות braitot based on whether they're like
chattel or whether they're like קרקע. karka. If you say that they're
like chattel, maybe I can make a distinction in the property and
not, even though אגב agav it shouldn't matter, we'll get to that
in a minute. But for now we're going to bracket that. If
they're like chattel, I could understand why it might matter and how
to resolve the two ברייתות braitot between whether the slaves are in
the land I'm taking possession of or not in the land. How
this work? היינו דעומדים בתוכה אין לא לא. Haynu de-omdim be-tokhah in
lo lo.
That's why it could work. I could say if they're in it,
it works, maybe because of קנין חצר kinyan chatzer or because of
קנין אגב. kinyan agav. So they need to be in the land.
But if they're not in the land, it doesn't work. So if
you treat them like chattel, I can work with both ברייתות. braitot.
It works, you know, the one that says you're קונה koneh when
you're קונה קרקע koneh karka is because they're in the land, and
when you're not, it's because they're separate from the land. אלא ללישנא
דאמר עבדי כקרקע דמי, Ella le-lishna de-amar avdi ke-karka dami,
but if they're like property, למה לי עומדים בתוכה, lamah li omdim
be-tokhah, why do I need them to be standing in the land?
הא אמר שמואל מכר לו עשר שדות בעשר מדינות כיון שהחזיק באחת
מהן קנה כולם. Ha amar Shmuel makhar lo eser sadot be-eser medinot
kivan she-hechzik be-achat me-hen kanah kulam. שמואל Shmuel says that actually yes,
whenever you take possession of one piece of land, that can work
for another piece of land even if it's very distant. I can
take possession of a piece of property in New York, and if
the seller is intending to sell it to me, that act of
taking possession can also allow me to take possession of his, of
you know, of a different piece of property in California. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says if this idea that one ברייתא braita says
you get the slaves with the land and one says you don't
and we're distinguishing whether the slave is in the, on the piece
of property or not, I could theoretically understand it matters if they're
chattel, although in a minute we're going to challenge that as well.
But there I could imagine chattel in a land works, not in
the land doesn't work. But if slaves are like property, שמואל Shmuel
says whenever you take possession of one piece of property, you can
take possession, if it's intended, of a different one even very distant.
So how do you reconcile these two ברייתות, braitot, how does it
matter standing in the land or not standing in the land? So
the גמרא Gemara says ולטעמיך ללישנא דאמר עבדי כמטלטלי דמי למה לי
עומד בתוכה? U-le-ta'amekha le-lishna de-amar avdi ke-metalteli dami lamah li omeid be-tokhah?
So now the גמרא Gemara pushes back: You know what, this distinction
standing in the land or not standing doesn't really work even if
you say they're like chattel, and this is for the reason we
were saying before, because אגב *agav* it doesn't have to be in
the land. הא קיימא לן דלא בעינן צבורין *Ha kayma lan delo
ba'inan tziburin*, the principle of אגב *agav* is that when you take
possession of קרקע *karka*, you can use you can take possession of
chattel even if it's not physically in the land. So either way
we've got a problem. Okay, whether you say slaves are like chattel
or whether you say they're like קרקע *karka*, we have one ברייתא
Beraita: *braita* that says it works when you take possession of קרקע
*karka* to take slaves and one says it doesn't. We distinguish whether
slaves are in the land or not in the land, but logically
none of that should matter because whether they're- if they're מטלטלין *metaltelin*,
they shouldn't need to be in the land to work for אגב
*agav*, and if they're קרקע *karka*, shouldn't need to be in the
land- one piece of קרקע *karka* works for another piece of קרקע
*karka*. So how do you make this distinction? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, אלא *Ella*, top of י"ב עמוד ב' *Yud Bet Amud
Bet*, אלא מאי אית לך למימר שאני מטלטלי דניידי ממטלטלי דלא ניידי
*Ella mai it lach lemeimar shani metalteli denaydi mimetalteli delo naydi*. So
if you're going to go the route of slaves are like מטלטלין
*metaltelin*, you would be forced to make a distinction between property that
moves and property that doesn't move. תוספות Tosfos. *Tosafot*, by the way,
says moves here means like a human being, a slave, not like
a cow. Okay, that when do we say that אגב *agav* works
even if something is not physically in the property? If it's basically
an inanimate object or it's a cow, it's not a human being.
In that type of a case, especially because then you could imagine
that the intent of the seller to sell it since these things
don't have a will of their own, the seller is like conceptually
combining it all in one package. And that's when אגב *agav* works
and the מטלטלין *metaltelin* are not physically present. But if you have
a slave that has an intellect and a will of his own,
it is not connected to the land you're selling unless he is
physically present
in the land. That's how to deal with that distinction. Similarly, if
you take the approach that slaves are like land, so we could
say the same type of thing. They're like land, but for this
idea that when you take possession in New York, it works for
a piece of land in California, that doesn't work with a slave.
Why? הכא נמי שאני מקרקעי דניידי ממקרקעי דלא ניידי *Hacha nami shani
mikarkaei denaydi mimikarkaei delo naydi*. There's even when you consider it to
be land, there's a difference between land that doesn't move and land
that does move. עבדא מקרקעי דניידי הוא *Avda mikarkaei denaydi hu*, and
a slave is basically land that moves. התם *Hatam*, and therefore when
I take possession of a piece of property in New York, the
slave doesn't go with it. Fundamentally, the slave is considered a free
agent and detached and so on, not a free agent, but whatever,
you know, not seen as one piece with a piece of land
in New York. And therefore that קנין *kinyan* of קרקע *karka* for
this other quote-unquote קרקע *karka* doesn't work. But for New York and
California, התם סדנא דארעא חד הוא *Hatam sadna de'ara chad hu*. The
crust of the land is all the same, meaning everything is connected,
we won't worry about separated by oceans, maybe also there there's the
ocean floor, but all land somehow is seen as one big piece
of land, it's just a few thousand miles away, but it's still
somehow part of the same same conceptual extended piece of land.
So therefore, that's why you can take possession of New York and
also take a piece of land in California, but that would not
be true by slaves. So what did we say? We have said
that even though slaves are basically, the principle is like קרקע *karka*
for normal הלכות halachot *halachot*, especially cases of like when they're exempt
from certain הלכות halachot *halachot*. When it comes to things like liens
and related to liens, פרוזבול *pruzbul*, and also this קנין *kinyan* of
אגב *agav*, you know, there we can discuss whether they are like
like land or like or like a chattel. עולא Ulla *Ulla* and
the נהרדעי *Nahardai* and all of these positions say that they're like
land and there are liens on them. And רב נחמן Rav Nachman
*Rav Nachman* says there are no liens on them. And now we
see that, okay, that's one question whether there are liens or not
liens. When it comes to these קנינים *kinyanim*, there could be a
lot of exceptions. So even if you think that slaves are are
like like land, it might in terms when you get to the
question about using them for אגב *agav*, it might not work to
do אגב *agav* with them because they're not like the, you know,
landed cities in יהודה *Yehuda* like the פסוק *pasuk*, and therefore it
doesn't work to have you know to have them the vehicle to
be קונה *koneh* chattel when you're through a קנין אגב *kinyan agav*,
even if normally they would be like land.
Similarly, the question about when you're קונה *koneh* land, when you start
with land, do you get the slaves as well? Even if the
slaves are like land, the answer might be no because they're, again,
independent, they move around. So being קונה *koneh* this piece of land
doesn't work for- it might work for a piece of land that's
physically distant, but it doesn't work for a slave. And if they're
like chattel, even though there's a thing called a קנין אגב *kinyan
agav*, again, that might not work by a slave that's under their
own volition, and therefore you might need the slave to actually physically
be in the on the property for it to work. So when
it comes to קנינים *kinyanim*, a lot of ways in which, you
know, there could be... can't really put them in a nice neat
category, and the debate of עולא and רב נחמן Rav Nachman seems
to much more be focused on this question about whether there are
liens that apply to slaves automatically like they do to land. Okay,
that was wrapping up statements of עולא in the name of רבי
אלעזר, Rav Elazar, and now we move to the next part of
the משנה, Mishnah, which is giving general principles about נזיקין, Nezikin, and
the next line is נכסים שאין בהם מעילה. Nechasim she'ein bahem me'ilah.
You only pay for damages done to property for which there is
no מעילה, Me'ilah, meaning stuff that is like חולין, chullin, you know,
or הדיוט, hedyot, נכסי הדיוט nechsei hedyot and not הקדש. Hekdesh. That
there is an exemption of נזק Nezek if the damaged property belongs
to הקדש. Hekdesh. So the גמרא Gemara says, but the משנה Mishnah
focuses on מעילה, Me'ilah, which is the particular קרבן korban that you
bring when you misuse הקדש, Hekdesh, and it only applies to certain
types of הקדש, Hekdesh, and other הקדש Hekdesh there is no קרבן
מעילה. korban Me'ilah. So it actually seems that there could be a
category of things that are sanctified that you would be liable to
pay if you damaged. So let us take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: נכסים שאין בהם מעילה. Nechasim
she'ein bahem me'ilah. מעילה הוא דלית בהו המקדש קדשי. Me'ilah hu d'leis
bo ha-mikdash kodshei. It is okay, there is no מעילה Me'ilah as
long as there is no מעילה Me'ilah you pay for damages even
if the thing is sanctified. So what is something that is sanctified
that there is no מעילה? Me'ilah? So the classic example is קדשים
קלים. Kodshim Kalim. Okay, קדשים קלים Kodshim Kalim is like a שלמים
Shelamim where the owner eats the meat, and the כהנים Kohanim eat
also the חזה ושוק chazeh v'shok and they eat a piece of
it. But the שלמים Shelamim is קדשים קלים Kodshim Kalim because it
can be eaten in all ירושלים Yerushalayim and it is eaten by
the owners, and there is no מעילה. Me'ilah. The only thing that
is מעילה Me'ilah by a שלמים Shelamim is the אימורים, eimurim, the
innards that are burnt on the מזבח mizbeach after the animal is
שחט shechted because that is the thing that is כולו להשם. kulo
l'Hashem. But the rest of it, the meat or whatever, no מעילה
Me'ilah at all. So that would seem to say that if my
animal gores a שלמים Shelamim of somebody else, I have to pay
even though it is sanctified because there is no מעילה, Me'ilah, there
still is going to be payment for נזק. Nezek. All right, so
what is that based on? So מאן תנא, man tana, who is
this תנא? tana? אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rebbe Yochanan, בקדשים קלים ואליבא
דרבי יוסי הגלילי. b'kodshim kalim v'aliba d'Rebbe Yosi HaGlili. The case would
be קדשים קלים, Kodshim Kalim, lighter sacrifices like I said, a שלמים,
Shelamim, and where there is no מעילה, Me'ilah, and it follows רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yosi HaGlili דאמר ממון בעלים הוא d'amar mammon ba'alim
hu because there is a classic position of רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi
that says that קדשים קלים Kodshim Kalim is considered to be even
though it is sanctified and it has to be brought up on
the מזבח, mizbeach, that is more about like its status, but that
is not about who owns it. You know, if you want to
use an analogy, I don't know, think about like a pair of
תפילין, Tefillin, right? It is or ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. You own
it, it is holy, it has holiness in it, but it is
owned by you. That he says is קדשים קלים. Kodshim Kalim. You
are the owner, you are going to bring it, you are going
to eat the meat. Okay, it has, you know, it has to
be sprinkled on the מזבח, mizbeach, the blood, you know, it is
קדוש, kadosh, the meat can only be eaten in certain places, but
it is yours. That is very different than if I donate my
car to הקדש Hekdesh which is owned by הקדש, Hekdesh, or even
קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim like a חטאת Chatas or an עולה Olah
which is basically not going to be eaten by me at all.
That is like it all belongs to הקדש, Hekdesh, but קדשים קלים,
Kodshim Kalim, that is ממון בעלים, mammon ba'alim, that is mine. And
because of that, that has a whole ramifications for הלכות halachos, where
for רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yosi HaGlili it is not exempted from
areas in which הקדש Hekdesh is exempt. And here too, if your
ox gores my שלמים, Shelamim, you have to pay me, it is
like it just gored my normal cow.
Okay,
דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: ומעלה מעל בהשם. u'ma'ala ma'al
b'Hashem. It says somebody, you know, swears falsely against his neighbor, denies
that he is watching an object for his neighbor, and because he
swears falsely, he is trespass against God, and he has to pay
back and he has to bring a special קרבן מעילה korban Me'ilah
and etc. אשם מעילה asham me'ilah etc. So the תורה Torah says
he trespasses against God through falsely using God's name, you know, in
an oath. But the teaching here of רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi is
that this can apply even by an object that is להשם. l'Hashem.
Even by some type of an object that is sanctified, you could
be denying your friend the right to it. It is fundamentally your
friend's and by denying and taking a false oath, you are stealing
from your friend and all these הלכות apply. So it is really
considered to belong to your friend even though it is להשם. l'Hashem.
Okay, so להשם לרבות קדשים קלים שהן ממונו דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי.
l'Hashem l'rabos kodshim kalim she-hein mammono divrei Rebbe Yosi HaGlili. So רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yosi HaGlili says that you are that that thing
that you are watching for your friend, that שלמים, Shelamim, that thing
is ומעלה מעל בהשם, u'ma'ala ma'al b'Hashem, there is sort of God's
thing here, but it is also וכחש בעמיתו, v'kichash b'amito, you are
denying it to your friend and therefore it is his property and
you have to pay.
Okay, that's so now that's it. So that is what our משנה,
Mishnah, our משנה Mishnah is saying is you can have קדשים Kodshim
that you pay for for damaging as long as there is no
מעילה, Me'ilah, as long as it is קדשים קלים. Kodshim Kalim. So
the גמרא Gemara says והתנן, v'hatnan, but didn't we teach in a
משנה, Mishnah, another משנה Mishnah in קידושין, Kiddushin, quoting a lot of
קידושין Kiddushin right now, המקדש בחלקו, Ha-mekadesh b'chelko, if a כהן Kohen
marries a woman with his portion... of a קרבן, korban, okay, בין
בקדשי קדשים בין בקדשים קלים, bein b'kodshei kodashim bein b'kodshim kalim, whether
it's his portion in a חטאת chatas or an עולה, olah, you
know, the leather of an עולה, olah, something that's קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim or even קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, the
חזה ושוק, chazei v'shok, the thigh and the breast of the animal,
you know, that the כהן kohen has a right to eat, if
he goes ahead and he says to a woman הרי את מקודשת
לי, Hare at mekudeshet li, the הלכה halacha is אינה מקודשת. eina
mekudeshet. She's not married to him. Okay. Even though now she might
have the ability to eat that meat, depending on if she's now
she's going to be married to a
כהן. kohen. So at least by the קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, the
wife of a
כהן kohen can eat the כהן גדול's kohen gadol portion, okay, or
she could sell it to another כהן. kohen. Anyway, so the point
is he went ahead and he gave this to her even though
it is something of value, she's not married. Why not? Because even
though he has a right to eat from it, it's not considered
his, it's not ממון בעלים. mammon ba'alim. We're going to see a
phrase at the contrast to ממון בעלים mammon ba'alim that the גמרא's
Gemara going to come with in a second, which is going to
be משלחן גבוה קזכו. mishulchan gavoa k'zachu. He's eating off of God's
table. So he's invited to eat from the meat, but it's not
his property so he's not giving her his property. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says look, that applies even to קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim,
so it seems like that's not going like רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabi
Yose HaGlili because רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabi Yose HaGlili would say at
least the קדשים קלים kodshim kalim is ממון בעלים. mammon ba'alim. Okay.
לימא דלא רבי יוסי הגלילי, Leima d'lo Rabi Yose HaGlili, let's say
that's not like רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabi Yose HaGlili. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, אפילו תימא רבי יוסי הגלילי. afilu teima Rabi Yose
HaGlili. That can even be רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabi Yose HaGlili. כי
אמר רבי יוסי הגלילי מחיים אבל לאחר שחיטה אפילו רבי יוסי הגלילי
מודה דכי קזכו משלחן גבוה קזכו. Ki amar Rabi Yose HaGlili michaiym
aval le'achar shechita afilu Rabi Yose HaGlili modeh d'ki k'zachu mishulchan gavoa
k'zachu. When did רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabi Yose HaGlili say that קדשים
קלים kodshim kalim was ממון בעלים mammon ba'alim when the animal was
still alive? Okay, it's my קרבן, korban, I'm going to go ahead
and bring it, it's mine, but once it's shechted and now we're
eating the meat, that's like God is inviting us to eat from
God's table, משלחן גבוה קזכו. mishulchan gavoa k'zachu. Then I'm no longer
eating mine, I'm eating something that is God's. Okay. So only when
it's alive is it still mine. Once it's shechted and brought as
a קרבן korban and being eaten from, we're eating from God's. And
that's why when the כהן kohen gives his portion of קדשים קלים
kodshim kalim to a woman, she's not מקודשת. mekudeshet. That works even
for רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabi Yose HaGlili because at that stage it
is no longer his. Now רש"י Rashi here says, by the way,
interesting debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosfos You know, רש"י Rashi
says that idea of משלחן גבוה קזכו mishulchan gavoa k'zachu even applies
to the owners when the owners are eating their portion, which really
means that for all of רבי יוסי הגלילי's Rabi Yose HaGlili הלכות,
the idea of that it's the owner's only applies when the animal
is alive. תוספות Tosfos makes a big distinction. תוספות says no, no,
no. When it comes to a שלמים, shelamim, it started off as
my cow, I'm eating my cow, anybody can eat the cow, not
only limited to כהנים, kohanim, it can be eaten in all of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So for the owner we do not say משלחן גבוה
קזכו. mishulchan gavoa k'zachu. The owner is always eating his שלמים, shelamim,
he's eating his own thing according to רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabi Yose
HaGlili. And if the owner used his part of the שלמים shelamim
to marry a woman, that would actually, even after it was shechted,
that would be
considered ממון הדיוט, mammon hedyot, that would be considered ממון בעלים. mammon
ba'alim. The כהן's kohen portion, however, כהנים kohanim are always eating off
of God's table. You know, it didn't start as the כהנים, kohanim,
the person offered it to God and now the כהן kohen gets
a piece of it. Okay, fine. So what is the גמרא Gemara
saying? רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabi Yose HaGlili says that by
שלמים, shelamim, certainly when it's a שלמים shelamim when it's alive, that's
considered to be the owner's. If your ox gores my שלמים shelamim
when it's alive, you have to pay me. We don't treat it
as belonging to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Once it's been shechted,
certainly at that point the כהנים's kohanim portion is considered to be
eating from God's table. But when it's alive, that is considered ממון
בעלים. mammon ba'alim. So now let's see if the גמרא's Gemara going
to challenge. Is that always true that when it's alive it's ממון
בעלים mammon ba'alim for רבי יוסי הגלילי? Rabi Yose HaGlili? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ומחיים אמר? U'michaiym amar? Does רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabi Yose HaGlili really say that when it's alive it's always
considered to be ממון בעלים? mammon ba'alim? והתניא, V'hatanya, we taught in
the משנה, mishna, בכור, bechor, if you have a firstborn animal, which
the הלכה halacha is it's given to the כהן kohen and brought
as a קרבן. korban. However, if it has a מום, mum, the
כהן kohen can shecht it and eat it outside the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash without bringing it as a קרבן. korban. So you have
a בכור. bechor. מוכרין אותו תם חי. Mochrin oso tam chai. If
it is unblemished and would have to be brought as a קרבן,
korban, and I give it to a כהן, kohen, the כהן kohen
can go ahead and sell it to another כהן, kohen, you know,
whatever, he can go ahead and sell it, and the other person
will bring it. Okay, so that's already a חידוש chiddush that you're
allowed to sell something that has to be brought as a קרבן.
korban. All right. ובעל מום, U'ba'al mum, if it has a blemish
and now could be shechted and eaten without being brought, חי ושחוט,
chai v'shachut, it could be sold whether it's alive or even after
it's shechted. It's just meat, it's just a normal thing that could
be eaten, it no longer is being brought as a קרבן. korban.
All right. ומקדשין בו את האשה, U'm-kadshin bo es ha-isha, and you
can go ahead head and use it to marry a woman. If
it's something you can sell, then you can use it to marry
a woman. So that basically means it's like it's your property, and
that would be a principle about ממון הדיוט. Mamon Hedyot. Now that
would work very nice. It's alive, right? None of these is when
it's been שחט shechted as a קרבן. Korban. It's either without a
blemish and alive, or it's has a blemish and is not going
to function as a קרבן, Korban, so it's alive or dead, all
those cases, ממון הדיוט. Mamon Hedyot. Works perfectly with the idea, let's
focus on the case of תמים Tamim when it could in theory
be brought as a קרבן, Korban, and nevertheless, while it's still alive,
the כהן Kohen can go ahead and can use it to marry
a woman, can sell it. This is the principle, seems perfect with
what we said, that when it's still alive, even though eventually it's
going to be brought as a קרבן, Korban, it's still ממון הדיוט.
Mamon Hedyot. Except we have a little problem. ואמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה, V'amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha, said רב
נחמן Rav Nachman. in the name of רבה בר אבוה, Rabba bar
Avuha,
לא שנו אלא בבכור בזמן הזה. Lo shanu ela b'bechor b'zman hazeh.
That is only true nowadays that there's no בית המקדש. Beis haMikdash.
דליכא דלא חזי להקרבה אית להו לכהן זכייה בגווייהו, d'leika d'lo chazi
l'hakrava is lu l'kohen zchiya b'gavayu, since it can't be brought as
a
קרבן, Korban, that's why the כהן Kohen is considered to be an
owner of this בכור bechor that is unblemished. Because it'll never be
brought as a קרבן, Korban, so therefore, eventually, what are you going
to do with it? With an unblemished thing? You're going to wait
for it to get a blemish and then you're going to eat
it. So it's seen as in the process of being a non
קרבן Korban and שחט shechted outside the בית המקדש Beis haMikdash because
there's no בית המקדש. Beis haMikdash. You're just waiting for it to
get a blemish. That's when I could say that it's like the
כהן Kohen owns it. That's when it's ממון בעלים. Mamon Balim. Okay.
אבל בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, Aval b'zman sheBeis haMikdash kayam, when there's
a בית המקדש, Beis haMikdash, דחזי להקרבה, d'chazi l'hakrava, that it could
be brought as a קרבן, Korban, לא, lo, then it's not considered
ממון בעלים. Mamon Balim. You can't sell it as a כהן. Kohen.
You can't be מקדש mekadesh an אשה. isha. So that seems to
be against the idea of רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose saying that when
it's alive and it's קדשים קלים, Kodshim Kalim, which is what a
בכור bechor is, it's ממון בעלים. Mamon Balim. Now maybe you could
say we're not going like רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yose. So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ואיתיביה רבא לרב נחמן, V'isivyeh Rava l'Rav Nachman, and רבא Rava challenged
רב נחמן. ומעלה מעל בה' לרבות קדשים קלים שהן ממונו דברי רבי
יוסי הגלילי. U'maala maal b'Hashem l'rabos Kodshim Kalim shehein mamono divrei Rebbi
Yose haGlili. He said, I don't understand, why do you have to
say that? Couldn't this work like רבי יוסי הגלילי? Rebbi Yose haGlili?
According to רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rebbi Yose haGlili, it's קדשים קלים, Kodshim
Kalim, this בכור, bechor, so even if there is a בית המקדש,
Beis haMikdash, it's still alive, let it function as ממון בעלים. Mamon
Balim. ומשני, U'meshani, and he answered, רבינא בבכור בחוץ לארץ ואליבא דרבי
שמעון. Ravina b'bechor b'chutz la'aretz v'aliba d'Rebbi Shimon. Rather than saying, you're
right, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yose haGlili actually does say that it's
ממון בעלים Mamon Balim when it's alive, it says, no, no, רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yose haGlili is only talking about a very special
case. When did רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yose haGlili say it's ממון
בעלים? Mamon Balim? He, similar to our case that there's no בית
המקדש, Beis haMikdash, it's a בכור bechor outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. And outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, following the position of
רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, either you're not supposed to bring it as
a קרבן, Korban, you're supposed to wait till it gets a מום,
mum, or you don't have to bring it as a קרבן, Korban,
but outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, it's on a path to
being a non קרבן. Korban. According to רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, בבכור
בחוץ לארץ אליבא דרבי שמעון דאמר אם באו תמימים יקרבו. b'bechor b'chutz
la'aretz aliba d'Rebbi Shimon d'amar im ba'u temimim yikrevu. If you bring
a בכור bechor that's unblemished from חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, you offer
it up on the מזבח. mizbeach. אם באו, im ba'u, if they're
brought, yes you bring it. לכתחילה לא, lechatchila lo, but you're not
obligated to, or maybe לכתחילה lechatchila you shouldn't. If it's outside of
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you're allowed to wait for it to get
a blemish. It's not on a path for הקרבה. hakrava. Similar to
the idea of בכור bechor nowadays. So here you have this was
a perfect case that seemed to be רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rebbi Yose
haGlili. It was a בכור, bechor, you could sell it, you could
marry a woman with it, and nevertheless, what we wound up saying
was was that only in a special case, no בית המקדש, Beis
haMikdash, outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, some special case, and we
did not want to say that רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yose haGlili
considered this to be ממון בעלים. Mamon Balim. So doesn't that go
against your general idea that רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yose haGlili is
willing to say that קדשים קלים Kodshim Kalim is ממון בעלים? Mamon
Balim? Here we're really really limiting רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yose haGlili
to a very special case. So ואי איתא, v'ei isah, and if
it's true, דאמר רבי יוסי הגלילי ממונו הוא מחיים, d'amar Rebbi Yose
haGlili mamono hu m'chayim, if רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose is willing to
say that at least when it's alive it's
ממון בעלים, Mamon Balim, in an unqualified way, so top of י"ג
עמוד א', yud gimmel amud aleph, לישני הא רבי יוסי הגלילי הא
רבנן. lishney ha Rebbi Yose haGlili ha Rabbanan.
Why not say that those that try to say we're talking about
a special case like it's outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or
no בית המקדש, Beis haMikdash, they don't agree to רבי יוסי. Rebbi
Yose. Okay, but according to רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rebbi Yose haGlili, yes,
even if there's a בית המקדש, Beis haMikdash, even if you're in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, right now, it's קדשים קלים Kodshim Kalim and
it's ממון בעלים. Mamon Balim. Why didn't we say that? Why did
we have to limit it to a special case? Doesn't this show
that רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yose haGlili does not really say that
it's ממון, mamon, that it's ממון בעלים Mamon Balim except in a
very narrow case? So the גמרא says... One minute, no. מתנות כהונה
קאמרת? Matnos kehuna kaamarta? What? You're talking about gifts to a כהן?
kohen? You're talking about a בכור? bechor? שאני מתנות כהונה דכי קא
זכי משולחן גבוה קא זכי. Shani matnos kehuna deki ka zachie meshulchan
gavoah ka zachie. No, no, no, no, no. מתנות כהונה, Matnas kehuna,
gifts to the כהן kohen are also from God's table. What does
this mean? It means when did רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili
say that something was ממון בעלים? mamon ba'alim? When it started off
as my cow. I sanctified it as a שלמים. shlamim. In that
case, it was my cow before, it's my cow now, I'm going
to eat the meat, I'm just going to bring it as a
קרבן. korban. Okay, it has sanctity just like a ספר תורה sefer
torah I own or תפילין tefillin I own has sanctity, but it's
mine. That's mine, your ox gores it, you pay me, all right?
That even though I'm going to be bringing this as a קרבן.
korban. That's what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili would say, that
מחיים, mechayim, the owner's קרבן korban that he sanctifies, right, that is
considered ממון בעלים. mamon ba'alim. However, the part that the כהן kohen
is going to get off of my שלמים shlamim didn't start as
the כהן's; kohen's; he's eating off of God's table. That's not ממון
בעלים. mamon ba'alim. You know what else? When I have a firstborn
animal and I give it to a כהן, kohen, he got it
because it was a בכור. bechor. He didn't start with it as
his as his sheep or his cow. In that case, again, he's
getting it as God's off of God's table. I essentially gave it
to God, God gave it to the כהן. kohen. מתנות כהונה Matnas
kehuna are just like what the כהן kohen gets after it's שחט.
shechted. That's משולחן גבוה קא זכי. meshulchan gavoah ka zachie. So when
we were talking about a בכור, bechor, the only way that would
be considered ממון mamon of the כהן kohen is if it's not
on the path towards הקרבה. hakrava. But if it's on the path
towards הקרבה, hakrava, since the כהן kohen only got it because it
was מתנות כהונה, matnos kehuna, that also would not be ממון בעלים.
mamon ba'alim. Okay, we will stop here.